<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="full2026"
     docName="draft-flm-openpgp-sync-01">
  <front>
    <!-- Working title. We'll want something that more accurately frames the system before we submit. It never also hurts to have a more catchy title... -->
    <title abbrev="OpenPGP Keylist Subscriptions">
      Safely Distributing OpenPGP Keys with Keylist Subscriptions
    </title>
    <!-- I don't care about the order of authors. Note that IETF consisters all named authors to have contributed equally. Feel free to reorder if you'd like. -->
    <author initials="M.M."
            surname="McCain"
            fullname="R. Miles McCain">
      <organization abbrev="FLM">First Look Media</organization>
      <email>ietf@sendmiles.email</email>
      <uri>https://rmrm.io</uri>
    </author>
    <author initials="M.L."
            surname="Lee"
            fullname="Micah F. Lee">
      <organization abbrev="TI">The Intercept</organization>
      <email>micah.lee@theintercept.com</email>
      <uri>https://micahflee.com/</uri>
    </author>
    <date month="July"
          year="2018" />
    <area>Security</area>
    <!-- Given that 'key management' is listed as a critical category of the 'Security' area, I believe that this I-D is best suited for the 'Security' area. ~MM -->
    <keyword>OpenPGP</keyword>
    <keyword>GPGSync</keyword>
    <keyword>GPG</keyword>
    <keyword>Keylist</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies a system by which clients may subscribe to an organization's
        keylist to keep its internal keystore up-to-date. Ensuring that all members
        of an organization have their colleagues' most recent PGP keys is critical
        to maintaining operational security. To enable cross-client compatibility,
        this document proposes a standard format for the keylist file as well as
        feature requirements for clients who wish to implement keylist subscription
        functionality.
      </t>
      <!-- We'll want to tighten this abstract up a bit... ~MM -->
    </abstract>
    <note/>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro"
             title="Introduction">
      <t>This document specifies a system by which OpenPGP clients may subscribe to
        a cryptographically signed keylist published by an organization. This system
        allows for seamless key rotation across an entire organization and enhances
        operational security. The user interface by which an OpenPGP client provides
        this functionality to the user is out of scope, as is the process by which
        the OpenPGP client retrieves keys. Other non-security-related implementation
        details are also out of scope. To enable cross-client compatibility, this
        document instead provides a standard format for the keylist, its cryptographic
        verification, and the method by which it is retreived over the Internet.
      </t>
      <section anchor="notation"
               title="Requirements Notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
          "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are
          to be interpreted as described in [RFC2119].
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="terminology"
               title="Terminology">
        <t>This document uses the terms "OpenPGP", "public key", "private key", "signature",
          "keystore", and "fingerprint" defined by OpenPGP Message Format [RFC4880].
        </t>
        <!-- TODO: verify that all the previous terms are actually defined in RFC4880. ~MM -->
        <!-- TODO: does 'URI' and 'Internet' need a citation? Probably not, but we should check. ~MM -->
        <t>The term "keylist" is defined as a list of OpenPGP keys identified by their
          fingerprints accessible via a URI. The exact format of this data is specified
          in "Data Element Formats". An "authority key" is defined as the OpenPGP
          used to sign a particular keylist. Every keylist has a corresponding authority
          key, and every authority key has at least one corresponding keylist. For
          security purposes, a single authority key SHOULD NOT be used to sign multiple
          keylists.
        </t>
        <!-- TODO: find out how to hyperlink sections. ~ MM -->
        <!-- TODO: I avoid using the word 'file' here as it has a nuanced meaning and really we're just talking about data accessible via a URI. Is there a term other than 'data' that is appropriate here? ~MM -->
      </section>
      <section anchor="functions"
               title="General Functions">
        <t>As new keys are created and other keys are revoked, it is critical that all
          members of an organization have the most recent set of keys available on
          their computers. Keylists enable organizations to publish a directory of
          OpenPGP keys that OpenPGP clients can use to keep their internal keystores
          up-to-date.
        </t>
        <section anchor="keylist-subscribe"
                 title="Subscribing to Keylists">
          <t>A single OpenPGP client may subscribe to many different keylists, or none
            at all. When an OpenPGP client first subscribes to a keylist, it SHOULD
            update or import every key present in the keylist. Keylist subscriptions
            SHOULD be persistent--that is, they should be permanently stored by the
            OpenPGP client to enable future automatic updates.</t>
          <t>To subscribe to a keylist, the OpenPGP client must be aware of the keylist
            URI, the keylist's signature URI, and the fingerprint of the authority
            key used to sign the keylist. An OpenPGP client MUST NOT employ a trust-on-first-use
            model for determining the fingerprint of the authority key; it must be
            explicitly provided by the user.</t>
          <!-- TODO: Should I not say 'user'? Is there a better way to phrase this? ~MM -->
        </section>
        <section anchor="keylist-update"
                 title="Periodic Updates">
          <t>The primary purpose of keylists is to enable periodic updates of OpenPGP
            clients' internal keystores. We RECOMMEND that OpenPGP clients provide
            a default refresh interval of less than one day, however we also RECOMMEND
            that OpenPGP clients allow the user to select this interval.</t>
          <t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="keylist-crypto"
                 title="Cryptographic Verification of Keylists">
          <!-- TODO -->
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="formats"
               title="Data Element Formats">
        <!-- TODO -->
        <section anchor="terms"
                 title="Keylist File">
          <!-- TODO -->
        </section>
        <section anchor="sigfile"
                 title="Signature File">
          <!-- TODO -->
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="retrieval"
               title="Data Retrieval">
        <!-- TODO -->
      </section>
      <!-- ... body text ... -->
      <section anchor="securityconsiderations"
               title="Security Considerations">
        <t>
          <!-- TODO, see https://tools.ietf.org/html/bcp72 -->
        </t>
      </section>
      <!-- TODO: other elements -->
  </middle>
  <back></back>
</rfc>
